Letters From lwo Jima
【硫 磺 岛 来 信】
lWO JlMA
(硫磺岛，2005年)
How did those soldiers ever manage to dig out these tunnels?
那些士兵是怎么挖出这些隧道？
Let's get a rotation in here.
我们换班吧
Hey, l found something!
喂，我发现东西了
小心点， 轻一点
小心
lWO JlMA 1944
(硫磺岛，1944年)
Hanako...
花子
We soldiers dig.
我们一直在挖
We dig all day.
我们整天都在挖
This is the hole that we will fight...
这将是我们以后打仗…
and die in.
死在里面的坑洞
Hanako...
花子
am I digging my own grave?
我是不是在自掘坟墓？
Today, I head for the post where my men await.
今天我前往士兵死守的硫磺岛
I am determined to serve and give my life for my country.
我决心为祖国， 赴汤蹈火、在死不惜
I believe I have organized everything at home...
我把家里都安排妥善
but I am sorry I wasn't able to attend to the kitchen floor before I left.
不过很抱歉来不及拖厨房地板
I had all the intention...
我本来要处理的
but had to leave without having the time...
不过必须赶着上路
and I am still worried about it.
我仍然有点担心
So make sure to have Taro take care of it promptly.
请你尽快叫太郎处理
Damn this island! The Americans can have it.
这座臭小岛，给美国佬算了
Nothing grows here.
这里什么都长不出来
lt smells. lt's hot. There are too many damn bugs, and there's no water.
又臭又热， 虫子又多，又没有水喝
This island is part of Japan's sacred homeland.
这座小岛是日本的神圣领土
There's nothing sacred about this island.
哪有什么神圣的地方
Saigo.
西乡
We should just give the island to the Americans...
我们应该供手让给美国佬
and then we can go home.
然后就可以回家
Saigo!
西乡！
What did you say, soldier?
你刚才说什么？
l said if we beat the Americans, then we can go home.
我们打败美国佬就能回家
You there, is that what he said?
他是这么说的吗？
Yes, sir.
是的，长官
l'm Kuribayashi.
我是栗林
Welcome, General. l am Admiral Ohsugi.
欢迎，中将，我是大杉准将
How long have you been waiting here for me?
你们在这里等了多久？
Three hours, sir.
三个钟头
Sorry to hear that.
真是不好意思
They wouldn't allow me to wire my arrival after what happened to Admiral Yamamoto.
山本大将的飞机被美军击落后， 上级就不让我发电通知你们
l understand, sir.
我了解，长官
This is my aide, Lieutenant Fujita.
这是我的副官，藤田中尉
What's the matter, Admiral? You don't look very well.
准将，你的脸色不太好
lt's nothing, sir. The water doesn't agree with me here.
没事，我只是喝不惯这里的水
Sorry to hear that.
很遗憾
This way to your quarters.
请到您的营房
Admiral, l want to make a round of the island first.
我想先巡视这座小岛
Shall l fetch a vehicle?
我替您调派专车
No, let's walk.
不用，我们走一走
Walking is good for the health.
走路有益健康
lt might be just what you need, Ohsugi.
也许你该多走路，大杉
So that's Suribachi.
那就是折钵山
You unpatriotic...
你们这两个不爱国
no-good peasants!
没用的农夫
Hey, stop it!
住手
Stand up!
站起来
What are you doing?
你在做什么？
These soldiers...
这两个小兵…
were conspiring with unpatriotic words, sir.
说了不爱国的话
l see.
原来如此
And, Captain, do you have such an excess of soldiers...
军曹，你有足够的士兵
that you could put two of them out of commission?
能把他们鞭打到不能打仗吗？
No, sir.
没有，长官
Then stop beating them.
那就不要再鞭打他们
Deny their lunch rations instead.
让他们中午饿肚子就行了
A good captain uses his brain, not just his whip.
一名好军曹要用脑子，不是鞭子
是的，长官
What is all this?
这些是什么？
All this?
这些吗？
Trenches, sir.
是战壕
Why are the men digging trenches here?
为什么在这里挖战壕？
This is where the Americans are expected to land.
美军会在这里登陆
Have them stop immediately.
命令他们立刻住手
But, General--
但是，中将…
And, Captain...
军曹
make sure these men get proper breaks.
让这些士兵休息一下
They look like they're from Mars.
他们看起来像火星人
Stop digging!
停止挖掘！
Just as well.
不吃饭也好
My stomach has been bothering me anyway.
我的肠胃不太舒服
A toast to General Kuribayashi...
敬栗林中将
a fine commander.
一位优秀的指挥官
Better than sake!
这比清酒好喝
l heard he lived in America.
我听说他住过美国
Maybe that's why he doesn't want us digging trenches.
也许他根本不要我们挖战壕
Maybe he likes Americans.
也许他喜欢美国佬
No, stupid. He studied the Americans.
才不咧，他是去了解美军
So now he knows how to beat them.
这样才知道该怎么打败他们
l heard from someone in the 204th...
我听204营的人说
that another general was supposed to command the island...
上头本来是找另外一名将军
but he didn't want the job.
可是他不肯来这里
So Premier Tojo gave it to Kuribayashi instead.
东条首相就把任务交给栗林
Nozaki, you hear a lot of things...
野崎，你听说不少事嘛
but your ears are full of wax!
可是你的耳朵都塞满耳屎
Anyway, you can't trust anyone from the 204th.
而且204营的人都不可靠
They're part of the Navy.
他们是海军
l think this Kuribayashi must be a superb general.
我觉得栗林是很棒的将军
Look...
瞧
we're not digging those damn trenches in the sand anymore, are we?
咱们不必挖臭战壕了
This heat is more than l had anticipated.
这里比我想像的更热
不用多礼
This island is bigger than l thought. l'm exhausted.
这座小岛也比我想像的更大， 我累死了
lto, reporting for duty.
伊藤中尉报到
Thank you for coming right away.
谢谢你立刻赶来
How much air force do we have available?
我们有多少空军的支援？
41Zekes and 13 bombers, sir.
四十一架战斗机、十三架轰炸机
ls that all?
就这样？
ln order to support Saipan, we lost 66 planes a few days ago.
他们支援塞班岛，失去六十六架飞机
We will have to rely on support from the Combined Fleet then.
那就只好靠联合舰队的支援了
ls this the current defense plan?
这就是目前的防御战略？
是的
And what about the Army troops? Where will they be stationed?
陆军部队驻守在哪里？
l don't know exactly.
我不确定
They are under independent command of Colonel Adachi.
他们接受安达中佐的指挥
You have not coordinated your plans with the Army?
你们没和陆军协调作战计划？
According to Navy rules, until the enemy lands--
根据海军军规，敌军登陆前…
This is a real war! You are aware of that, aren't you?
这是真的战争，你们不知道吗？
This will not work.
这样行不通
You are concentrating all your efforts on the beaches.
你们把军力都集中在滩头
- Move the artillery to higher ground. - But, sir, we just had them...
把炮队移到制高点， 我们才刚把他们…
moved down to the beaches.
移到滩头
Well, move them back.
那就把他们移回去
Coordinate with the Army and have them start immediately.
和陆军联系，请他们立刻行动
Fortifications at Suribachi are the priority.
折钵山的防御工事是第一优先
l'm going to walk some more.
我要再出去走走
- lt's pitch black out there, sir. - l know.
长官，外面一片漆黑， 我知道
This one is trouble.
这家伙是个麻烦
Army commanders usually are, sir.
陆军指挥官都很麻烦
Another letter?
又要寄信喔？
You know that the mail only goes out when there's a boat available?
船来了才能把信寄出去
l have a lot of family.
我有很多家人
Then how come all your letters are addressed to your wife?
为什么收信人都是你老婆？
Nosey!
多管闲事
Here, let me do you a favor.
让我帮你个忙
Otherwise, your letters will never make it through.
不然你的信永远寄不出去
Hey, what are you doing?
你在干什么？
l used to work at the censorship office in Tokyo before l was transferred.
我被调职前在东京稽查局工作
You mean demoted.
你应该是被降职吧
''To Hanako: We soldiers dig. We dig all day.''
花子，我们一直挖，整天都在挖
No, no, no. This will never pass.
不行，这一定过不了关
Give me that back!
还给我
There. You'll thank me for this later, Saigo.
好了，你会感激我的，西乡
Next!
下一个
Good!
很好
专心点
西乡
Are you blind?
你是瞎了吗？
Can't you see the target?
看不到标靶吗？
Even my six-year-old could shoot better than you do.
连我六岁的儿子都射得比你准
Do it again!
再来一次
You're an embarrassment! You call yourself an lmperial soldier?
真丢脸，你算是帝国士兵吗？
Tonight you will clean the boots of your entire troop.
你今晚要替部队的弟兄擦军靴
Go to the rear!
给我到后面去
They should learn to clean their guns properly, rather than their boots.
他们应该学会擦步枪，不是军靴
What are those tanks doing here?
这些坦克车怎么会在这里？
Those are out of commission, sir. They are waiting for parts.
它们坏了，正在等零件
- For how long? - About a month, sir.
要等多久？ 大概一个月
Taro, America is filled with cars.
太郎，美国有好多车子
I have to be very careful when I cross the street...
我每次过马路都要很小心
there are so many cars everywhere.
到处都是车子
Taro, are you behaving yourself and listening to your mother?
你有没有乖乖听妈妈的话？
I miss you.
爸爸很想你
藤田
These civilians need to be evacuated as soon as possible.
尽快让平民撤退
Yes, sir.
是的，长官
Hanako...
花子
we have a celebrity here.
这里来了一个名人
Baron Nishi, the Olympic gold medalist in horse jumping.
奥运马术项目金牌得主， 西竹一男爵
He will lead the 26th tank regiment...
他才刚从东京抵达
and has just arrived from Tokyo.
要负责指挥26战车团
回去工作
Nishi is very handsome, and there are rumors of his womanizing skills.
竹一很帅，听说他很会钓马子
But there are no women left on the island to woo.
不过岛上连一个女人都没有
Lieutenant Colonel Nishi! You brought your horse.
西中佐，你把你的马带来了
From Chichi Jima.
大老远从父岛带来
l used to be a cavalryman myself, you know.
我以前也是骑兵
Of course, l know.
我知道
l've been looking forward to serving under you.
我很期待能在您的麾下服役
One who understands horses the way l do.
您和我一样了解马匹
When we used to ride horses through the battlefield...
我们以前都是骑着马上战场
those were the good old days...
能够骑马真好
not like these mechanized contraptions.
不像这些机械军车
l could send for another horse...
我再调一匹马
and we could ride together.
我们一起骑马
l'm afraid my riding days are over.
我已经不能骑马了
But tell me about this famous horse of yours that you won the Olympics with.
谈谈替你赢了奥运金牌的那匹马
My stallion, Uranus.
我的爱马，天王星
Oh, yes, this horse has a fine back.
这真是一匹好马
l bought him in ltaly.
他是我在意大利买的
They were happy to get rid of him.
他们很高兴能把他卖掉
He was such a wild horse.
他是一匹野马
No one could tame the beast, but l told them...
没人能驯服他，不过我说…
such a headstrong horse...
这种野马
is a perfect match for me.
最适合我
Come dine with me tonight. l feel like having a drink.
今晚一起吃饭，我想小酌几杯
l think that can be arranged.
没问题
How did you manage to get the Johnnie Walker?
你怎么弄得到约翰走路？
l drank some already.
我已经喝了一点
l'm sorry. This is all we have.
不好意思，只有这点菜
That's fine, as long as we have this.
没关系，有酒就行
What is this empty plate?
怎么会有空盘子？
l have told our cook that all officers will have the same rations and food as our men.
我跟厨子说军官和士兵吃的一样
l'm sorry, but serving three dishes is regulation.
抱歉，规定要上三道菜
Oh, but of course we have the right to be served more than three dishes per meal.
我们当然有权吃不只三道菜
You're absolutely right.
你说的没错
When you think about it...
老实说
it is regrettable that most of the Combined Fleet was destroyed.
联合舰队几乎全毁真的很遗憾
We still have some battleships left...
虽然还剩下几艘军舰
but we have very little striking power from the air or sea.
但是海空的火力都荡然无存
Nishi, what do you mean?
竹一，你在说什么？
So you have not heard about the Mariana battle?
您没有听说马里尼亚诺战役？
Admiral Ozawa's carrier and boat planes were destroyed.
大泽中将的航空母舰和战机全毁
The lmperial headquarters...
帝国总部
is deceiving not just the people, but us as well.
不但欺骗人民也欺骗我们
lf you want my honest opinion, General...
如果您想听我的意见
the best thing to do...
最好的方法就是…
would be to sink the island to the bottom of the sea.
把这座小岛炸沉到海底
And yet, you still came?
但是你还是来了
Well...
我猜
l figured your men were going to need all the tanks that l could bring.
你们应该需要， 我带来的坦克车
请吧
This must be it.
一定是这里
Yes, the enemy must land here.
敌军一定会在这里登陆
Run!
快跑！
Like you were one of the Americans!
假装你是美军
Go on! Which direction would you take?
快跑！你会往哪个方向跑？
快跑！不要偷懒
快跑…
Hey...
喂…
l think your general has gone mad.
你那个将军疯了
Look at the gun he has.
你看他的配枪
He probably took it from a dead American.
一定是从死美军身上抢来的
Maybe.
也许吧
Break time is over.
休息时间结束
Back to work!
回去干活
Are you all right, Kashiwara?
柏原，你没事吧？
You look pale.
你的脸色好苍白
l'm fine. lt's just the damn water.
我没事，只是水不干净
But...l...really...need to go.
不过…我得去…上大号
There will be a major change in our strategy.
防御战略要大幅修改
We will dig caves in the Motoyama, Higashiyama, and Suribachi-yama areas.
我们要在元山、东山， 折钵山挖掘洞穴
We will build these underground fortifications, and fight to the end.
搭建地下碉堡、奋战到底
- What about the beach defenses, sir? - Not needed.
如何布署滩头防御？ 不需要
But, sir, the beach trenches are our first line of defense.
可是滩头战壕是第一线防御
Without the beach trenches, how do you expect us to win?
没有战壕该怎么打赢敌军？
Hayashi, do you know how many cars America produces in a year?
林少将， 你知道美国每年生产几辆汽车？
Five million.
五百万辆
The Americans' technological advancements cannot be underestimated.
我们不能低估美军的技术优势
They will cross the beaches eventually.
他们一定会攻占滩头
lf we waste our soldiers there, there is no hope for victory.
牺牲太多士兵就无法获得胜利
lt is inevitable that men will die...
士兵的伤亡无法避免
but l never heard of an island operation without beach fortifications.
我没听过不运用滩头堡的防御战
General, it will be a futile waste of time to start digging tunnels now.
现在开始挖掘隧道是浪费时间
We should force the enemy near the island...
我们应该趁敌军接近小岛
and launch a pincer drive from the sea and air.
从海空展开钳形攻势
l agree. That makes the most sense.
我同意，这样最有效
Ohsugi...
大杉
doesn't the Navy know?
海军难道不知情吗？
The Combined Fleet has been completely destroyed off the Marianas.
联合舰队在马里尼亚诺战役全毁
The island is now isolated.
硫磺岛已经完全孤立
What's more, l received a new order from the lmperial headquarters this morning.
今早我收到帝国总部的新命令
The remaining fighter planes are to be sent back to Tokyo to defend the mainland.
仅存的战机要调回东京捍卫本土
Outrageous! How are we to fight?
荒唐！我们该怎么作战？
We do not have time for discussion. We should head back.
没时间讨论了，赶快回去吧
Dear Mother...
敬爱的母亲大人
I have been commissioned to a new troop today.
我今天被调派到新的部队
I cannot talk about this transfer now.
我不能透露太多细节
Take good care of yourself.
请您务必保重身体
Look at this picture.
看看这张照片
That's some fancy castle.
好豪华的城堡哦
You know who this castle was built for?
你知道这是替谁盖的吗？
Someone who was already dead.
一个死掉的人
They must have had a lot of money back then...
他们一定很有钱
to build a castle like that for a dead person.
才能替死人盖城堡
Why are you reading that book anyway?
你干嘛看那本书？
We're never going to war over there.
我们又不会去那里打仗
We'll be lucky if we even get a hole in the ground when we're dead.
我们死了能埋在地下就很好了
Don't talk about that. lt's bad luck.
别说这种不吉利的话
ls this the 312th?
请问是312营吗？
That's right.
没错
l'm Nozaki. This is Saigo.
我是野崎，他是西乡
我是清水
Shimizu, you can put your bedroll there.
清水，把铺盖放在这里
There's an empty space in the back.
后面有一个空位
Don't mind him.
别管他
His friend Kashiwara just died.
他的朋友柏原才刚死
That used to be his spot.
那本来是他的铺位
But we are all going to die.
不过我们都会死
That's the plan, isn't it?
不是这样吗？
For our country, it is an honor.
为国捐躯是一种光荣
Kashiwara died of honorable dysentery.
柏原是因为光荣的痢疾而死
Shimizu, where are you from?
清水，你是哪里人？
Kanagawa-ken.
神奈川县
Ozawa is from there, aren't you?
小泽也是那里人，对吧？
That's right.
没错
Where were you trained?
你在哪里受训？
Maybe we were at the same school?
也许我们念同一所军校
No.
不可能
l trained in Tokyo.
我是在东京受训
l trained in Tokyo, too. Where?
我也一样，东京哪里？
The koho kimmu Yoin Yoseijo.
后方勤务人员训练中心
Hey...
嘿…
why do you think they put a kempeitai in our unit?
他们为什么派宪兵来这里？
l don't know.
我不知道
He's not wearing the white armband. He's not kempeitai.
他没戴白色臂章，不是宪兵
He went to the kempeitai military academy.
他念的是宪兵军校
Maybe he was kicked out.
也许他被开除了
He acts like a kempeitai.
他看起来像是宪兵
Look at his holster. That's not standard issue.
他的枪套跟我们的不同
He's been put here to spy on us.
肯定是来监视我们的
Why would he spy on us?
他干嘛监视我们？
Maybe it's those letters you've been writing.
也许是因为你写的那些信
You should be careful.
你最好小心点
Weed soup again?
又是杂草汤？
Kuribayashi is conserving our food supplies for the battle.
栗林下令为战争保留食粮
We'll be dead before the Americans even get here.
美军攻来之前我们都会饿死
And you would think that with all my war effort contributions...
我为战争贡献了那么多
we should be eating kasutera cakes or sandwiches.
咱们应该吃蜂蜜蛋糕和三明治
What?
什么？
l ran a bakery in Ohmiya with my wife.
我和老婆在大宫开面包店
Back when we could still get sugar...
还有砂糖配给的时候
we sold ampan and kasutera cakes.
我们卖红豆面包和蜂蜜蛋糕
However, his kempeitai brethren...
不过他的宪兵弟兄们
used to come and take whatever they wanted.
经常跑来想拿什么就拿什么
For the war...
说是为了战争
For the country...
为了国家
Why bread?
为什么要拿面包？
We ran into those types at our clothing store as well.
我们的服饰店也经常碰到这种事
When we started making sandwiches...
我们做的三明治
they took those, too.
也被他们拿走
And when we ran out of meat and just had bread, they still came.
后来没肉只做面包，照样被拿走
Eventually, they took all of our baking equipment for the metal...
最后他们连烘焙器材都拿去
and we were out of business.
我们只好关门大吉
l should have been a fisherman.
我应该去当渔夫
lt must have been hard on your wife...
你太太一定很辛苦
without the shop and without her husband.
面包店没了，丈夫又不在
Tell them to go away. We have nothing to sell.
请他们走，我们没东西卖了
Congratulations! Your husband is going to war.
恭喜，你先生被征召入伍
Thank you very much.
谢谢你们
l'm happy to serve the country.
我很高兴能为国家效力
Prayers for your eternal success at arms.
我祈求你能凯旋归国
l beg of you! We have only each other.
求求你，我们只能互相依赖
This is not the time.
你在抱怨什么？
We have all sent our husbands and sons to war.
我们的丈夫儿子都被派去打仗
We all have to do our part.
每个人都要尽他的义务
At least you'll have a little one to carry on your name.
至少你们家还能留下后代
花子
l can't eat with you like that.
你一直哭我都吃不下饭
What am l going to do after you die?
你死了以后我该怎么办？
l'm not in the coffin yet.
我又还没有进棺材
The men never come home, not even a soul.
当兵的男人没有一个活着回来
They'll never let you come home.
他们不会让你回家
Don't worry.
别担心
And now, with the baby.
我现在又怀了小宝宝
Can you hear me?
你听得见吗？
lt's Dad.
我是爸爸
Listen.
听好了
Don't tell anyone what l'm telling you now.
我说的话别告诉任何人
lt's a secret.
这是秘密
Your dad...
你爸爸…
is going to come home for you.
一定会为了你回家
Hurry up!
快点
The enemy approaches!
敌军要攻来了
This is ridiculous!
这太荒谬了
Why waste time digging these tunnels?
干嘛浪费时间挖隧道？
They are all going to die anyway.
反正他们死定了
At least he conceded to the pillboxes on the beach.
至少他同意在滩头布署地堡
You wanted to see me, sir?
长官，您要见我？
Care for a drink?
喝一杯吗？
You have been looking quite pale these days.
你这几天脸色很苍白
lt's the water. lt has never agreed with me.
我一直喝不惯这里的水
That's not good.
这样对身体不好
Why don't you go back to the mainland to recoup?
你何不回去本土好好休养？
l have commissioned Admiral lchimaru to take your place.
我征调市丸准将接替你的职务
We are wasting time digging these tunnels.
挖掘隧道是浪费时间
General, the island won't last five days without fleet support.
没有联合舰队支援，撑不了五天
We should fight to the death.
我们应该誓死奋战
The tunnel-digging may be futile.
挖掘隧道也许没有用
Maybe the stand on lwo will be futile.
捍卫硫磺岛也许也没有用
Maybe the whole war is futile.
也许这场战争根本就没有意义
But will you give up then?
但是你会放弃吗？
We will defend this island until we are dead!
我们要捍卫硫磺岛，奋战到底
Until the very last soldier is dead!
直到最后一名士兵战死为止
lf our children can live safely for one more day...
只要能让日本的孩童多活一天
it would be worth the one more day that we defend this island!
我们誓死奋战就是值得的
Ohsugi...
大杉
if you have an ounce of pride left as an officer...
如果你还有一丝身为军官的尊严
l beg of you...
我请求你
go back to headquarters and ask them to send support.
回到总部要求他们派出支援
So the rumor is true? l couldn't believe it.
谣言果然是真的，我不敢相信
l'm grateful to be leaving this island.
我能离开这里感到无限感激
We may have had our differences...
我们也许意见相左
but l'm truly sorry to see you go.
但是看到你要离开，我很难过
General Hayashi, it is up to you now.
林少将，现在要靠你了
Kuribayashi belongs behind a desk, not commanding war.
栗林只会纸上谈兵，不会打仗
l understand.
我知道
There are many of us who agree with you, sir.
有很多人的想法都和你一样
Listen.
听好了
The Americans are likely to land here.
美军很可能在这里登陆
Crossfire positions will be here...
交战位置会在这里…
here...
这里…
and here.
和这里
The fact is...
事实是…
we are completely outnumbered in every sector.
我们在每一方面都处于劣势
But we have a great advantage.
但是我们有一个很大的优势
Can anyone tell me what that is?
有人能告诉我吗？
The Americans are weak-willed and inferior to Japanese soldiers.
美军比日军软弱和低劣
Very good, Shimizu.
很好，清水
Why is that?
为什么？
They are not as disciplined...
他们比较没有纪律
and they let their emotions interfere with their duty.
而且会让感情影响他们的职责
That is correct.
没错
Here is the uniform of an American medic.
这是美军看护兵的制服
He should be your target.
他是你们的主要目标
For Americans will risk the lives of many soldiers to save this one.
美军为了保护他会牺牲很多士兵
Understood?
了解吗？
General, may l speak with you?
中将，我能跟您说句话吗？
Please keep an eye on Major General Hayashi.
请您留意林少将
Thank you for your concern, Nishi...
谢谢你的关心，竹一
but we don't have any time to waste.
不过我们不能浪费时间
We must think about what we can do at this moment.
一定要想想现在能做什么
Admiral lchimaru.
市丸准将
Reporting for duty, sir.
我前来报到，长官
Excuse me.
恕我告退
Thank you for coming on such short notice.
多谢你临时赶来
Jupiter!
木星！
Jupiter.
木星
好乖…好乖…
Yamazaki...
山崎
what are you doing just sitting there? Help us--
别光坐着，来帮我们…
l think he's writing about us in his reports.
他一定在写关于我们的报告
He's just writing a letter.
他只是在写信而已
lt's been two months, Nozaki.
都过了两个月了，野崎
He would have reported us by now.
他要的话早就检举我们了
How can you be sure?
你怎么能确定？
Will they ever stop?
他们连一刻都不肯停吗？
Day and night, day and night...
白天也炸，晚上也炸
lt's driving me crazy!
我都快被逼疯了！
lf the damn Americans are going to invade...
如果臭美国佬要进攻
why don't they hurry up and land?
为什么不赶快登陆？
Tako-Chan...
贵子
the four chicks that were born two months ago have grown so much.
两个月前出生的四只小鸡长大了
The mother chicken leads them for food every day...
母鸡每天都带着他们觅食
but they're giving me a hard time, picking at the vegetable garden I have grown.
不过他们都跑进我的菜园， 让我非常伤脑筋
The fleet of American ships has left Saipan.
美军舰队已经离开塞班岛
So they are on their way.
他们随时都会攻来
Ready the troops.
下令部队集合
Men...
弟兄们
the time has come to show your true colors.
你们展现胆量的时候来了
As a member of the honorable lmperial Army...
身为光荣的帝国陆军士兵
l trust that you will fight with honor.
我相信你们会奋勇作战
This island is of utmost importance to Japan.
这座小岛对日本非常重要
Should the island fall...
万一这座小岛沦陷
the enemy...
敌军就会…
will use it as their base to attack our homeland.
利用它做为基地， 攻击我们的家园
For the mainland...
为了捍卫本土
For our homeland...
和我们的家园
Until the very last man.
每一个人都要誓死奋战
Our duty is to stop the enemy right here.
我们的职责是阻止敌军的攻势
Not one of you...
每一名士兵…
is allowed to die until you have killed 10 enemy soldiers.
都要击毙十名敌军才能死
Do not expect to return home alive.
不要期待能活着回家
l will always be in front of you.
我一定会身先士卒
Long live the Emperor.
天皇陛下
万岁…， 万岁…
Take care and be well.
你要好好保重
I will fight courageously until the end, in the spirit of Yamato.
我会以大和精神勇敢誓死奋战
My heart will always be with you.
我的心将永远与你们同在
Takeichi.
竹一笔
Every household is assigned a quota of bag-making for the gunpowder.
家家户户都分配到一袋火药
I cannot help but get tense when I think that these will be used in battle.
我一想到可能会用到就很紧张
Taro and Yoko laugh at me for this.
太郎和优子老是笑我
Takako, on evacuation in Nagano, is also doing well.
撤退到长野的贵子也很好
I pray for your safety.
我祈祷你安全无恙
Sincerely, Yoshi.
妻笔
No one can shoot me now.
没有人能射死我了
That's a nice belt. My wife sent me one, too.
很棒的千人针腹卷， 我老婆也寄给我一条
Doesn't look like Mr. kempeitai has a thousand-stitch belt, does he?
看来宪兵先生并没有，对吧？
Maybe he thinks it will clash with his uniform.
也许他觉得和制服不搭配
He probably doesn't believe in superstitions, anyway.
搞不好他不信这一套
His mother made him one after all.
他母亲还是替他做了一条
- Maybe they're trying to sink the island. - My head hurts.
也许美军想炸沉硫磺岛， 我的头好痛
How many ships do you think there are out there?
你想美军派出几艘战舰？
At least 30. Maybe even 50.
至少三十艘，也许五十艘
- They must be really close. - l need to take a leak.
他们一定很接近了， 我得去小便
Don't go near the sewers. Dysentery is spreading through there.
别去粪坑，会染上痢疾
Where do l go then?
那我要去哪里？
There is a pot at the end of the cave.
山洞尽头有一个粪桶
The shit pot is full.
粪桶装满了
Someone needs to throw it out.
有人得拿出去倒
西乡
是
lf anything happens to that pot...
要是你把粪桶弄丢
you'll be carrying our shit away with your hands.
你就用手来接我们的大便
遵命
ls this some kind of a joke?
你在开我玩笑吗？
Why are you always picking on me?
我为什么老是这么倒楣？
Thank you, God. l take back what l said before.
神啊，谢了，我收回刚才的话
Shall we commence fire?
我们要开火吗？
Not yet.
还不行
The men wish to commence firing.
弟兄们想要开火
Hold your fire!
全员备战
全员备战！
Hold your fire!
They will take the beach in no time if we do not resist.
再不反击美军就会抢下滩头
Wait until the beach is full.
先等滩头都挤满了美军
Let's go. Commence firing!
好了，开火！
Commence firing!
开火！
攻击！
The guns of the Kitakubo unit were destroyed.
北久保部队的机关枪被炸毁
All the pillbox units on the beach have been destroyed.
滩头堡的部队全数阵亡
However, all other forces are intact...
但是其它部队都没事
and we estimate more than 1,000 enemy casualties.
我们估计有一千名敌军伤亡
The pillbox destruction was unavoidable.
滩头堡部队一定会阵亡
Overall, that is good news.
整体来说，这仍是好消息
How are the men holding up at Suribachi?
折钵山的士兵如何？
Forces are intact.
仍然坚守岗位
很好
What is the enemy situation?
大约有多少敌军？
Approximately 20,000 men and 80 tanks.
两万名士兵和八十辆坦克车
There has to be more than that. They still have men waiting in the boats.
军舰上一定有更多士兵准备登陆
Currently the enemy front extends...
目前敌军占领了
between Suribachi and the south landing...
折钵山和千鸟机场
and Chidori airfield south.
以南的范围
Just as l thought... Suribachi and the Motoyama airfield.
果然被我料中， 折钵山和元山机场
They are making a two-pronged attack.
他们从两面夹击
我们盯住他们了！
继续移动！
That's not enough! l need more ammo.
不够，我需要更多弹药
Take his place!
过来代替他！
- The machine gun is blasted. - Use your rifle!
机关枪被炸毁了， 用你的步枪
Watch out! lmbecile!
小心，蠢蛋
l can't rely on you.
你太不可靠了
Go send a report to Colonel Adachi that we need another machine gun.
跟安达中佐说我们需要机关枪
Hurry up!
快去！
Colonel Adachi is asking for reinforcements.
安达中佐要求支援
We can't afford to send reinforcements. Tell him to hold out.
没有办法，叫他死守下去
Shoot him!
那边！开枪！
- What's the matter? - We're out of bullets!
怎么了？ 没子弹了
掩护我！
We are losing Suribachi.
折钵山被敌军占领
All is lost. Request permission to lead a suicide mission.
我们输定了， 请求自杀谢罪
No. You must try to hold them off.
不行，你们要抵挡敌军
Do what you can to survive and join forces in the north caves.
尽全力加入北洞穴的军力
But, sir...
但是，长官…
l have failed to hold Suribachi.
我没有守住折钵山
Permit me to die with honor with my men.
请准许我和士兵光荣自杀
No, Colonel.
不行
This is an order!
这是命令
Adachi.
安达！
Adachi!
Sir, Captain Tanida requests machine guns.
谷田军曹要更多机关枪
lt's over.
没希望了
Suicide...
唯一的选择…
That's the only thing left.
就是自杀
But--
但是…
Here, take this to your commander.
把这个拿给你的指挥官
l heard General Kuribayashi order Colonel Adachi to escape.
我听到栗林将军命令安达中佐逃命
Quiet!
闭嘴！
Escape is the coward's way.
只有懦夫才会逃命
Sit down!
坐下
Men...
弟兄们
we are...
我们是…
honorable soldiers of the Emperor.
天皇麾下光荣的士兵
Don't ever forget that.
千万不要忘记
The only way left for us...
我们唯一的选择…
is to die with honor.
就是尊严地自杀
This is our fate...
我们的命运
to find our place at Yasukuni Shrine.
是进入靖国神社
l'll see you there.
我会在那里再见到你们
天皇万岁
万岁…， 万岁…
Soldiers, farewell!
弟兄们，永别了
Stop!
站住！
You should die like an honorable soldier.
你应该像一个光荣的士兵自杀
Look, Shimizu...
清水，听好
we can still join the troops in the northern caves.
我们可以加入北洞穴的军力
Our orders are to stay here until death.
我们的命令是留下来自杀
l heard General Kuribayashi himself.
我亲耳听到栗林将军的命令
That's what he said...
他透过无线电
over the radio.
叫我们逃命
lt's true.
是真的
We can die here...
我们可以死在这里
or we can continue fighting.
也可以继续奋战到底
Which would better serve the Emperor?
怎么做才算是效忠天皇？
Which one?
你说呢？
Where does this go?
这里会通到哪里？
lt will take us closer to Motoyama.
通到接近元山的地方
Do you have orders to move back?
你们奉命撤退吗？
Where are the rest of your men?
其他的弟兄呢？
All dead.
全都死了
lt's the same with us.
我们的弟兄们也一样
There should be an outlet somewhere near here.
这附近应该有出路
Be quiet!
安静！
快逃！
So you thought you could blow us up, or burn us alive, did you?
你以为你能把我们活活烧死？
不！求求你们！
- Have we heard from Suribachi? - No, sir.
有来自折钵山的消息吗？ 没有
Send a messenger!
派传令兵去！
Lieutenant Oiso has ordered us to rendezvous at the east cave.
大矶中尉命令我们到北洞穴集合
We will make a run for Motoyama.
我们要冲到元山
There is no cover for two kilometers.
两公里的距离没有掩护
lt will be every man for himself.
大家只能自求多福
See you on the other side.
到了另一边再见
lf not on this earth, then in the next world.
如果活不了，那就来生再见
Don't run with the herd. That's where the enemy will fire.
不要跟着别人，会被敌军射死
Stay back.
退到后面
That's cowardice!
这是懦弱的行为
There is no use for a dead soldier.
一个死大兵没什么用吧
冲呀！
Wait until the flare is gone.
等到照明弹熄灭
我看不见他们， 不要停！
Crawl forward.
匐匍前进
What happened to the messenger?
传令兵在哪里？
He never came back.
他没有回来
l will go to Adachi myself.
我自己去找安达
Motoyama's transmitter still works, General.
元山部队的无线电打得通
Why not try there, sir?
何不试着联络他们？
Sir, these men retreated from Mt. Suribachi.
这些士兵从折钵山撤退过来
What are your names?
你们叫什么？
Saigo, from the 312th.
西乡，312营
Shimizu, reporting for duty.
清水，报到
You escaped from Suribachi?
你们从折钵山逃出来？
How dare you!
好大的狗胆！
lt was your duty to stay in your position until death.
你们的职责是坚守岗位
You should have died...
和同胞弟兄
with your fellow troop members.
一起壮烈牺牲
You are both a disgrace.
你们是日军的耻辱
Get on your knees.
跪下来
- But, sir-- - l said, get on your knees!
可是…， 我叫你们跪下来
l don't want you to kill my soldiers needlessly.
不准滥杀我的士兵
Put down your sword.
把武士刀放下来
Put it down!
放下来！
What's going on here?
这是怎么回事？
These men ran from Suribachi.
他们从折钵山逃出来
Lt. lto, l gave the order that all survivors retreat to the north caves.
伊藤中尉， 我下令生还者撤退到北洞穴
l am very sorry, General.
对不起，将军
lt's just...
但是…
Suribachi...
折钵山…
has fallen.
被攻占了
Now that Suribachi has been taken...
折钵山被攻占后
the enemy will maneuver all forces onto the hillside.
敌军会调派全部军力到山腰
We must move our command center north, sir.
我们必须把指挥部迁到北方
lto...
伊藤
fight for your fallen brethren...
为了你的阵亡弟兄…
until the end.
奋战到底
Get up!
起来
Major General Hayashi is leading an attack.
林少将要指挥一波攻击行动
We are to join him.
我们要去加入他们
可是…
Kuribayashi's orders are to remain in the caves.
栗林的命令是留在洞穴
Lieutenant lto says Kuribayashi is a weak American sympathizer.
伊藤说栗林是软弱的美军同路者
We will take back Mt. Suribachi.
我们一定要抢回折钵山
遵命！
Where is Major General Hayashi?
林少将在哪里？
We don't know, sir.
我们不知道
Who is in charge here?
这里由谁指挥？
l'm not sure.
我不确定
Stay here until l determine the plan of action.
先留在这里，等我想出战略再说
万岁，冲呀！
We're dead.
我们死定了
Pull back!
撤退
We'll get reinforcements.
我们会找到支援
扶他起来，别停！
这东西卡住了， 真没用
Why didn't your regiment join the attack?
你们的部队为什么不加入突击？
Don't sit here like rats!
别像胆小鼠辈光是坐着
Come out of your caves and fight!
大胆地出来奋勇抗敌
Where is your commander?
你们的指挥官呢？
We haven't received the order to attack.
我没收到攻击指令
Didn't you receive the order from General Hayashi?
你没收到林少将的命令吗？
Kuribayashi countermanded Hayashi's order.
栗林驳回林少将的命令
There is to be no attack.
暂时不进行攻击
We will take back Suribachi...
我才不管栗林怎么说
with or without Kuribayashi.
一定要抢回折钵山
There are already troops on the attack. Get your men in order.
攻击已经展开，命令士兵出发
Lieutenant, may l remind you of your rank!
中尉，我的军阶比你高
Your disrespect for senior officers...
你枉顾上级的命令
puts your men at needless risk.
让士兵冒不必要的风险
l suggest you go back to your cave...
我建议你回到岗位
or hand over your men.
或是把这些士兵交给我
Enough.
够了
We'll do it ourselves.
我们要自己去
That's against regulations.
这样是违反军纪
That's the officer who tried to kill us. He doesn't care.
他想砍死我们，才不要跟他去咧
l won't go back.
我不会回去
l've had enough of cave fighting.
我受够了窝在洞穴里
You men are now under Lieutenant Colonel Nishi's command.
你们现在受西中佐的指挥
l will throw myself under an enemy tank.
我要展开自杀攻击
l will take out one of their machines.
抱着地雷炸毁敌军战车
爱现， 这里有人
好吧， 搞什么？
Hurry.
尽快
What is the status?
战况如何？
A thousand men were lost...
一千名士兵
in a night attack along Chidori airfield.
在千鸟机场自杀
Why? l have given them strict orders not to kill themselves.
为什么？我下令不准自杀
lt seems that the order to retreat was not conveyed to all sectors.
撤退命令没有传达到每支部队
Hayashi.
林少将
Damn you!
你真该死
And the American advancement?
美军进攻到哪里？
A battalion is headed north and we are fighting back along the west ridge.
有一营美军向北进攻， 我们沿着西岭一带反击
Good. Once they cross the west ridge, they will be surrounded on three sides.
很好， 美军越过西岭会遭到三面夹击
This just arrived.
刚刚收到电报
Read it.
念出来
From headquarters...
总部急电
''We regret that we are unable to send reinforcements to lwo at this time.
很遗憾目前无法支援硫磺岛
We earnestly hope you will fight honorably...
我们衷心冀望你们誓死奋战
and die for your country.''
为祖国壮烈牺牲
攻击
中佐
Bring him in.
把他带进来
Shall l finish him off?
您要我把他解决掉吗？
No. Treat him.
不，替他医治
But, sir--
但是…
Okubo, you would expect the same, wouldn't you?
你也希望美军替你医治吧？
Endo, treat him.
远藤，替他医治
We are low on morphine as it is.
我们的吗啡存量不够
Sir, the Americans would not treat a wounded Japanese soldier.
美军绝对不会医治日本伤兵
Son, have you ever met one?
小子，你见过美军吗？
Treat him.
替他医治
Where are you, American tanks?
该死的美国战车，开哪去了？
Come and get me!
快给我过来！
远藤
How is the prisoner doing?
战俘的情况如何？
He is awake, sir.
他醒了
l will question the prisoner for information.
我要讯问战俘敌方军情
大兵，你来自哪里？
海军陆战队，A连
陆战队员
我是问你的家乡
我在加州住过一段时间
你知道玛丽毕克馥， 或是道格拉斯范朋克吗？
大家都知道他们
他们是我的朋友
我在东京的住所招待过他们
真的假的？你是名人吗？
我参加过1932年洛杉矶奥运
你是说真的吗？
这是我和…
我的马的参赛照片
真不是盖的
奥克拉荷马州
我来自那里
我是西竹一
我是山姆
Damn.
可恶
l've had enough of this.
我受够了
l'm going to surrender.
我要投降
Go ahead and arrest me.
尽管逮捕我吧
l don't care anymore. That's what you were put here for, isn't it?
我不管了， 你不是来监视我们的吗？
To report treasonous thoughts.
检举我们叛国的思想
l was put here because...
我来这里的原因是…
l was discharged from the kempeitai.
我被宪兵队开除
Discharged?
开除？
l had only been in service for five days.
我只服役了五天
Shimizu...
清水
you must always be firm.
你一定要心狠手辣
Any mercy and people will take advantage of you.
不然就会被老百姓骑到头上
That's unpatriotic.
这户人家不爱国
Go sort it out, Shimizu.
把他们揪出来
You do not have the lmperial flag properly displayed.
为何你们没有悬挂帝国国旗？
l'm sorry.
对不起
My husband has gone to war and l couldn't put it up myself.
我先生入伍，我自己挂不上去
lt is unpatriotic not to have the flag displayed.
不悬挂国旗就是不爱国
lf you help me, l'll put it up now.
请你帮我把它挂上去
Get that dog to shut up.
让那只臭狗闭嘴
What was that, sir?
您说什么？
That dog is a nuisance. lt is disruptive of Army communications.
那只狗会干扰军队的通讯
l am very sorry, sir.
真是对不起
五郎
安静！安静！
Shimizu. Dispose of the dog.
清水，把小狗解决掉
We can't have a dog interfering with important military commands.
不能让一只小狗干扰重要军令
Take the dog in the back.
把小狗带到后面
lt's only a dog.
他只是一只狗
lt won't happen again.
以后不会乱吠了
Take it out back.
把他带到后面
Keep the children inside.
带小孩子进去
Hurry up.
快点
Take the dog into the house and keep him quiet...
把狗带进屋里，别让他乱吠
and never let him out.
千万别让他跑出去
真是多谢你了
lt's taken care of, sir.
长官，已经解决了
Are you trying to make a fool out of me?
你把我当傻瓜吗？
lf you can't even shoot a dog, you'll never be able to handle the Reds.
你连一只小狗不敢射杀， 就对付不了共产党
You are unpatriotic!
你根本就不爱国
l was discharged for insubordination...
我因为不服从命令被开除
and sent here.
然后被调派到这里
原来如此
Don't look so glum, Shimizu.
别哭丧着一副脸
At least now only the enemy hates you.
至少现在只有敌军恨你
l don't blame the dog.
我并不怪那只小狗
Taro...
太郎
tonight I attended my farewell party.
今晚我出席我的惜别晚宴
The wives also attended, so there was a lot of fuss.
军官夫人也来了
Greeting all the ladies...
我得一一向她们致意
kept me from enjoying the food.
害我无法好好享用大餐
各位先生女士，请注意
今晚的贵宾来自日本帝国
栗林上校
这份礼物代表我们的友谊
1911年份寇特点四五手枪
每名骑兵都应该使用的配枪
谢谢你这份美好的礼物和友谊
我会想念你的， 不客气
各位，请就座，享用晚餐
谢谢
真漂亮
让我来问栗林上校
你不介意我叫你粟上校吧？
上校？
你对美日战争有什么看法？
我相信他们会是很好的盟军
她是说美国和日本打仗
日本最不应该和美国打仗
但是万一不幸发生战争
我将为祖国尽忠职守
我老公和你作战，你会射杀他？
我会遵守我的信念
你的信念
或是国家的信念？
难道有所不同吗？
你果然是真正的军人
那就太糟糕了
老公，这代表你死定了
不，绝对不会
山姆？
ls there any information of the enemy's plan?
这上面有敌军的战略吗？
No, it's just a letter.
没有，这只是一封信
lt's from his mother.
来自他的母亲
''Sam...
山姆
l have mailed you a couple of books to read.
我寄了几本书给你看
l hope that you like them.
希望你会喜欢
Yesterday...
昨天…
the dogs dug a hole under the fence.
家里的狗在篱笆下挖了洞
They ran all over the neighborhood.
钻到邻居家的院子乱跑
By the time we found them...
等我们找到他们
the Harrisons' roosters were terrorized.
哈里逊家的公鸡被吓坏了
Don't worry about us.
别替我们担心
Just take care of yourself and come back safely.
你要好好保重，安全回家
Remember what l said to you...
记住我跟你说过的话
always do what is right...
永远要做正确的事
because it is right.
因为这样做才对
l pray for a speedy end to the war...
我祈祷战争尽快结束
and your safe return.
你能早日安全归来
Love, Mom.''
爱你的母亲
敌袭！炸弹！
快点！快点！
攻击！
中佐！
远藤！远藤！
l'm sorry, sir. There is no more medicine.
中佐！， 对不起，药物用完了
lt's all right. l'm useless now. Go help the others!
算了，我没用了，去救别人吧
快去
Okubo, come here.
大久保，过来
How are we on ammunition?
弹药还剩多少？
Not good, sir.
不多
Our mortars have been taken out...
迫击炮全毁
and we're out of machine gun ammo.
机关枪的弹药也耗尽
We have only our rifles.
我们只剩下步枪
Okubo...
大久保
you are now in charge of the men.
你负责指挥连队
We can no longer hold this area.
这地方已经守不住了
You must guide the rest of the men north.
你要带领他们向北前进
Take whatever food and ammo we have left.
把剩下的粮食和弹药带走
What about you, sir?
长官，那您呢？
l'm tired of sharing this cave with all of you.
我受够了和你们挤在这个洞穴
l'm a one-man show from here on out.
我要一个人好好享用一下
What are you talking about, sir?
您在说什么？
Your first order of business...
你的第一个指令
is to find some water.
是要找到水
Men...
弟兄们
do your best.
尽全力奋战
Do what is right...
永远要做正确的事
because it is right.
因为这样做才对
Understood?
明白吗？
是， 是
l will make sure that they send you medicine and food.
我会请他们送药物和粮食给你
lt has been a great honor...
西联队长， 能够在您的麾下服役
to serve...
让我感到…
under you.
无比的光荣
出发
大久保
Hand me my rifle.
把我的步枪给我
l'm sorry, Okubo.
对不起，大久保
Why am l not getting any reports? Have we heard from Admiral lchimaru?
怎么都没报告？市丸准将没消息？
- No, sir. - What about Nishi or Hayashi?
没有，长官， 西中佐或林少将呢？
- Send out messengers! - We have. Many times.
派出传令兵， 我们派了很多个
None of them have come back.
没有一个回来
You can't plan strategy like this!
这样不能策划战略
西乡
l have been thinking about what Lt. Colonel Nishi said.
我在想西中佐说的话
He's right.
他说的对
l don't know anything about the enemy.
我对敌军一无所知
l believed that the Americans were cowards...
我以为美军都是懦夫
but they weren't.
但是他们并不是
l was taught...
军校的教官说
that they were savages...
他们都是野蛮人
but that American soldier...
但是那个美国大兵…
his mother's words...
他母亲说的话…
were the same as my mother's.
跟我母亲说的话一样
l want to fulfill my duty for the general...
我想要为将军尽忠职守
and our country...
为祖国壮烈牺牲
but l don't want to die for nothing.
但是我不想毫无意义地死去
What do you think?
你觉得呢？
You...
你...
haven't lived enough to realize...
还没有足够的历练， 让你了解到
what you are sacrificing.
你在为什么牺牲
Will you surrender with me?
你肯和我一起投降吗？
Careful.
小心点
They'll notice if we leave together. You go first.
我们一起走会被看到， 你先走
l'll make up an excuse.
我替你找一个藉口
After a while, l'll tell them l'm going to check on you.
然后我会说我要去找你
We'll be gone before they even notice.
趁他们不注意偷溜
Pretend that you have dysentery.
假装你有痢疾
Give me your dysentery look.
装出你快忍不住的样子
l guess that'll have to do.
我猜这样就行了
Where are you going?
你要去哪里？
l've got dysentery.
我有痢疾
You're going to surrender, aren't you?
你要去投降，对吧？
lf you are, take me with you.
带我一起去
- l've had enough of this war. - Be quiet!
我受够了这场战争， 安静！
Where are you going?
你们要去哪里？
He said he wasn't feeling well. lt could be dysentery.
他不太舒服，可能是痢疾
You two! Stop!
你们给我站住
Sir, maybe they got spooked.
也许他们只是被吓到
Miura, you're on guard.
三浦，你负责站岗
Make sure we have no more deserters.
确定不再有逃兵
长官，山岭上面
掩护他
别开枪
小心点
让他蹲下
有没有武器？
给他水喝
把他带过来
我们要出发了
这两名战俘怎么办？
你们两个留下来看守
走吧，弟兄们，出发
上吧
What unit were you with?
你来自哪支部队？
Higashiyama 314th.
东山314营
真是有够衰
咱们要看守他们一整晚吗？
Did you hear...
你有没有听说？
l heard that they would give you a meal.
他们会给战俘吃一顿饭
A meal...
吃一顿饭
That sounds good.
听起来不错
把他们带到滩头， 别开玩笑了
l'm from Yokohama, too.
我也来自横滨
After this is over, you can come visit me.
战争结束，你可以来找我
带着他们目标太明显了
我有更好的主意
Lieutenant!
中尉！
Let this be a lesson to anyone else...
谁想要投降
who wants to surrender.
这就是他们的下场
We need to get through the crossfire to reach the north...
我们必须穿过交叉火线
and join our forces at the front.
加入北方前线的部队
Listen.
听好了
We'll head for that cave and make our way from there.
先冲进那个洞穴再继续前进
Don't waste a bullet!
不要浪费子弹
Not a single one.
一颗都不能浪费
Don't shoot recklessly.
也不要乱开枪
退后！
快跑，快跑…
These are Nishi's troops and the survivors from Suribachi.
竹一的士兵和折钵山的生还者
Are there no officers?
没有军官吗？
You all did a good job making it here.
你们能撑到这里做得很好
Fujita, water for them.
藤田，给他们水喝
l'm sorry, sir. There is no more water.
抱歉，没有水了
l'm sorry.
对不起
At least you can rest.
至少你们可以休息
You look familiar.
你很眼熟
You almost lost your head.
你差点就被砍头
That was the second time you saved me.
那是您第二次救我一命
The first time...
第一次
was the day you landed on the island.
是您来到硫磺岛的那天
Of course. l remember.
我记得了
Well, everything happens in threes.
凡事都有第三次
Hanako...
花子
This letter will probably never get to you...
你可能永远收不到这封信
but...
但是…
it comforts me to write.
写信能安抚我的心情
For five days, we've been without water and food.
五天来我们没水喝，没东西吃
To survive...
为了活下去
we do unspeakable things.
我们做出可怕的事
There is no escape now.
现在我们逃不出去了
But...
但是…
my only concern is for you and the baby.
我只关心你和小宝宝
Dig up some worms.
又挖到几条蚯蚓
The battle is approaching its end...
这场战役接近尾声
and there is no more ammunition, no more water.
我们没有弹药和饮水
All the survivors will engage in a general attack.
仅存的士兵要一鼓作气进攻
I pray for the victory and safety of the Empire.
我要为胜利和帝国的安全祈祷
I bid you farewell.
也要向你们道别
For the country, I could not fulfill all of my duties.
我无法完成对祖国应尽的职责
Now that we have no ammunition, it is with regret that we must perish.
我们的弹药耗尽， 全体官兵必将阵亡
You made it all the way from Suribachi?
你大老远从折钵山过来？
That must have been quite a journey.
这趟旅程一定很惊险
You are quite a soldier.
你是一名好士兵
No, sir.
不，长官
l'm just a simple baker.
我只是个面包师傅
You were a baker?
你是面包师傅？
Any family?
有家人吗？
A wife...
一个妻子
and a baby girl born last summer in Ohmiya.
和去年夏天在大宫出生的女儿
l haven't met her yet.
我还没见过她
lt's strange.
真的很讽刺
l promised myself to fight until death for my family...
我对自己承诺要为家人誓死奋战
but the thought of my family makes it difficult to keep that promise.
但一想到家人就很难信守承诺
将军
A radio transmission from the homeland.
国内传来的无线电信息
For General kuribayashi...
献给栗林中将
and his troops, who are fighting bravely for our country...
以及他的部队， 他们为祖国奋战不懈
a song will be sung by the children of Nagano, which is kuribayashi's hometown.
来自栗林家乡的长野儿童合唱团， 为你们献唱一首歌曲
On the waves of the Pacific
矗立在太平洋的波浪之上
down south from the Imperial City
位于帝国皇宫以南
a small lonely island floats
这座小岛浮沉在海上
The fate of our Imperial country
帝国的命运
lies in the hands of this island
座落于她的手中
Iwo Jima
硫磺岛
As long as we stand
只要硫磺岛屹立不摇
we shall feel safe, as the Imperial land
人民就感到安全，帝国圣地…
shall forever be at peace
也永远和平巩固
We shall fight with pride and honor at any price
捍卫这座
Our proud island
令人骄傲的小岛
Iwo Jima
硫磺岛
Do me a favor.
帮我个忙
Stay here and burn all these documents, and my military chest.
留下来烧毁文件和我的军事箱
Everything happens in threes.
凡事都有第三次
We will make a general attack.
我们要展开总攻击
Although Japan has lost...
虽然日本战败
one day...
有一天
our people will praise your dedication.
人民会尊崇你们的贡献
A day will come when they will weep and pray for your souls.
他们也会为你们的亡魂祈祷哭泣
Be proud to die for your country.
骄傲地为祖国壮烈牺牲
l will always be in front of you.
我会永远身先士卒
冲呀！
全面开火！
将军
小心
掩护他
别开枪
No more.
够了
Thank you, Fujita.
辛苦你了
This is an order.
这是命令
You again.
又是你
l have one more favor to ask of you.
我要你再帮我一个忙
Bury me...
把我埋起来
so that no one will find me.
别让任何人找到我
Taro...
太郎
I will be home soon.
我很快就会回家
I'm glad to be going back to Japan...
我很高兴能回到日本
but I'm a bit sad to leave my friends behind.
但是向朋友道别也很难过
I drove home...
我开车回家
but...
但是…
it's lonely driving all by myself.
一个人开车好寂寞
ls this still Japanese soil?
这里仍是日本领土吗？
This is still Japan.
这里仍是日本
小心，也许有诡雷
小心
安全了
看我找到什么
有一个躲了起来
把他带过来
把铲子放下来
有人会说日语吗？
放轻松
你没事
让我把他解决掉
没人会伤害你
上尉，你要我射死他吗？ 不，不要开枪
别乱来
他发疯了
快点，我们准备走了
我们没水了
Be careful.
小心点
把它弄出来
导演：克林伊斯威特
剧本：山下艾瑞丝
故事：山下艾瑞丝， 保罗哈吉斯
制片：克林伊斯威特， 史蒂芬史匹柏
制片：劳勃罗伦兹
主演：渡边谦
主演：二宫和也
主演：伊原刚志
主演：加濑亮
主演：中村狮童